ELROND [IN SINDARIN]: (Anirne hene beriad i chên lîn...)
(ned Imladris nauthant e le beriathar aen.)
[CHANTS IN SINDARIN] Sleep Caradhras, be still, lie still...
(Losto Caradhras, sedho, hodo...
...hold [your wrath]!
(...nuitho [i 'ruith!])
SARUMAN [CHANTS IN QUENYA]: Wake up cruel Redhorn!
(Cuiva nwalca Carnirassë!)
May your blood-stained horn...
(Nai yarvaxëa rasselya...)
...shall fall upon the enemy-heads!
(...taltuva ñotto-carinnar!)
Wake up cruel...
(Cuiva nwalca...)
...Redhorn!
(...Carnirassë!)
[IN SINDARIN] Gate of the Elves, open now for me!
(Annon Edhellen, edro hi ammen.)
Doorway of the Dwarf-folk, listen to the word of my tongue.
(Fennas Nogothrim, lasto beth lammen.)
[IN SINDARIN] Gate of Elves...
(Ando Eldarinwa...)
...listen to my word,
(...a lasta quettanya,)
Threshold of Dwarves!
(Fenda Casarinwa!)
GIMLI [IN KHUZDÛL]:
(Kheled-zâram... Balin tazlifi.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Mae govannen, Legolas Thranduilion.)
(Govannas vîn gwennen le, Haldir o Lórien.)
(A Aragorn in Dúnedain...)
(istannen le ammen.)
Haldir.
[IN KHUZDÛL] I spit upon your grave.
(Ishkhaqwi ai durugnul.)
ARAGORN [URGENTLY IN SINDARIN]: We need your protection.
(Boe ammen veriad lîn.)
The road is fell!
(Andelu i ven!)
I'm glad we came to you.
(Merin le telim.)
We need your support!
(Boe ammen i dulu lîn!)
HALDIR:
Aragorn...
(...Eärendil.)
I'm glad we came to you.
(Merin le telim.)
The road is too dangerous.
(Andelu i ven.)
[SINGING IN SINDARIN] The bonds cut,
(In gwidh ristennin,)
[CHORUS IN QUENYA] Our regret is undying
(Ilfirin nairelma)
the spirit rent (i fae narchannen)
[CHORUS] What should be... (Nauva i...)
The Flame of Anor (I lach Anor ed)
[CHORUS] shall be. (...nauva.)
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying (Ilfirin nairelma)
from earth departed (ardhon gwannen)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
Mithrandir, (Mithrandir,)
O Pilgrim Grey (A Randir Vithren)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
You will not wander... (Ú-reniathach...)
[CHORUS] What should be shall be. (Nauva i nauva.)
the world green (i amar galen)
[CHORUS] Love... (Melme...)
[CHORUS] ...for this land... (...nóren sina...)
Your journey in... (I reniad lín ne...)
[CHORUS] is our lament. (nairelma.)
darkness, ended (môr, nuithannen.)
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying
(Ilfirin nairelma)
[CHORUS] Is deeper than the sea's...
(Núra lá earo...)
[CHORUS] ...depths
(...núri)
[IN SINDARIN] (Le aphadar aen.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Am meleth dîn,)
I ant e guil Arwen Undómiel pígatha.
[IN SINDARIN] (Aníron i e broniatha ad ae periatham,)
(athar i methid en-amar hen.)
(Aníron i e círatha na Valannor.)
[IN QUENYA] (Namárië.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Nadath nâ i moe cerich.)
But...
(Dan...)
(Ú-'eveditham...)
(Elessar.)
VOICE OF THE RING: They will fall.
(A'ghi gûr'ruzh.)
[v1.2]