GALADRIEL [IN SINDARIN]:
(I amar prestar aen.)
(Han mathon ne nen.)
(Han mathon ne chae.)
(A han noston ned 'wilith.)
[IN SINDARIN] Hold positions!
(Tangado haid!)
Release the arrows!
(Leithio i philinn!)
Positions!
(Haid!)
VOICE OF THE RING [WHISPERS IN BLACK SPEECH]:  Sauron...
(Zigur...)
[SINGING IN SINDARIN]  O Queen beyond the Western Seas!
(A Bereth thar Ennui Aeair!)
O light to us that wander
(Calad ammen i reniar)
Amid the tree-woven lands of Middle-earth.
(Mi 'aladhremmin ennorath.)
O Elbereth Star-kindler
(A Elbereth Gilthoniel)
your eyes and breath like shining jewels...
(i chin a thûl lín míriel...)
STRIDER [HUMS IN SINDARIN]:  Tinúviel the elven-fair
(Tinúviel elvanui)
Immortal maiden...
(Elleth alfirin...)
...elven-wise
(...edhelhael)
About him cast her night-dark hair
(O hon ring finnil fuinui)
And arms like silver...
(A renc gelebrin...)
VOICE OF THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  In the void...
(Gûm-ishi...)
Only...
(Ashi...)
Death...
(Gurum...)
VOICE OF THE RING:  Where the Shadows lie...
(Makha Gulshu darulu...)
In the Land of Mordor where Shadows lie.
(Daghburz-ishi makha Gulshu darulu.)
[SINGING IN QUENYA]  The earth groans
(I cemen nurrua)
And the wind...
(Ar i sure...)
...the wind...
(...i súre...)
...is crying!
(...naina!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Im Arwen - telin le thaed.)
(Lasto beth nîn...)
(Tolo dan nan galad.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Dartho guin Beriain - rych le ad tolthathon.)
(Hon mabathon - rochon ellint im.)
(Andelu i ven.)
ARWEN: [Frodo is dying.] (Frodo fîr. Ae athradon i hîr...)
(...tûr gwaith nîn beriatha hon.)
[IN SINDARIN] As you wish.
(Be iest lîn.)
[IN SINDARIN] Ride fast, Asfaloth, ride fast!
(Noro lim, Asfaloth, noro lim!)
Ride fast, Asfaloth!
(Noro lim, Asfaloth!)
[IN SINDARIN] Waters of the Misty Mountains, listen to the great word;
(Nîn o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer;)
flow waters of Loudwater, against the Ringwraiths!
(rimmo nîn Bruinen, dan in Ulaer!)
Waters of the Misty Mountains, listen to the great word;
(Nîn o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer;)
flow waters of Loudwater, against the Ringwraiths!
(rimmo nîn Bruinen, dan in Ulaer!)
[IN SINDARIN] Hear my voice. Come back to the light.
(Lasto beth nîn. Tolo dan nan galad.)
[IN SINDARIN] (A si i-Dhúath ú-orthor, Aragorn.)
(Ú or le... a ú or nin.)
(Renich i lú i erui govannem?)
(Nauthannen i ned ôl reniannen.)
(Gwenwin in enninath.)
(Ú-'arnech in naeth i si celich.)
(Renich i beth i pennen?)
THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  In the cold...
(Kelkum-ishi...)
[CHANTS IN BLACK SPEECH] One Ring...
(Ash Nazg...)
...to rule them all... [THE RING] One Ring to rule them all...
(...durbatulûk...) (Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
...One Ring to bring them all... Seven dwarf-lords' blood.
(...Ash Nazg thrakatulûk...) (Ombi kuzddurb sherkuk.)
In the cold, for the Dark Lord...
(Kelkum-ishi, Burz-Durbagu...)
...and in the darkness... ...in the darkness...
(...agh burzum-ishi...) (...burzum-ishi...)
...bind them!
(...krimpatul!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Havo dad, Legolas.)
THE RING:  In the Land of Mordor where...
(Daghburz-ishi makha...)
...your blood.
(...sherkuk.)
THE RING:  In the Land of Mordor where shadows lie.
(Daghburz-ishi makha gulshu darulu.)
THE RING:  Where the Shadows lie...
(Makha Gulshu darulu...)
THE RING:  One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
ELROND [IN SINDARIN]: (Anirne hene beriad i chên lîn...)
(ned Imladris nauthant e le beriathar aen.)
[SARUMAN CHANTS IN QUENYA]:  Wake up...
(Cuiva...)
[SARUMAN CHANTS, ECHOING]:  ...cruel...
(...nwalca...)
[SARUMAN CHANTS]:  ...Redhorn!
(...Carnirassë!)
[SARUMAN CHANTS]:  It shall fall upon the enemy-heads!
(Taltuva ñotto-carinnar!)
[CHANTS IN SINDARIN] Sleep Caradhras, be still, lie still...
(Losto Caradhras, sedho, hodo...
...hold!
(...nuitho!)
SARUMAN [CHANTS IN QUENYA]:  Wake up cruel Redhorn!
(Cuiva nwalca Carnirassë!)
May your blood-stained horn...
(Nai yarvaxëa rasselya...)
...shall fall upon the enemy-heads!
(...taltuva ñotto-carinnar!)
Wake up cruel...
(Cuiva nwalca...)
...Redhorn!
(...Carnirassë!)
[IN SINDARIN] Gate of the Elves, open now for me!
(Annon Edhellen, edro hi ammen.)
Doorway of the Dwarf-folk, listen to the word of my tongue.
(Fennas Nogothrim, lasto beth lammen.)
[GANDALF SPEAKS IN KHUZDÛL]
[IN SINDARIN] Gate of Elves...
(Ando Eldarinwa...)
...listen to my word,
(...a lasta quettanya,)
Threshold of Dwarves!
(Fenda Casarinwa!)
GANDALF, SOFTLY: Doorway of the Dwarf-folk...
(Fennas Nogothrim...)
GANDALF: ...listen to the word of my tongue.
(...lasto beth lammen.)
GANDALF:  Gate of Elves...
(Ando Eldarinwa...)
GIMLI, SOFTLY [IN KHUZDÛL]:  A crown of stars in the waters...
(Kilmîn malur ni zâram...)
...cold and black, of the Kheled-zâram. Balin sleeps.
(...kalil ra narag, Kheled-zâram... Balin tazlifi.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Mae govannen, Legolas Thranduilion.)
(Govannas vîn gwennen le, Haldir o Lórien.)
(A Aragorn in Dúnedain...)
(istannen le ammen.)
Haldir.
GIMLI [IN KHUZDÛL]:  May my excrement be poured...
(Îsh kakhfê...)
...upon the naked-jawed [beardless].
(...ai-'d-dûr-rugnul.)
ARAGORN [URGENTLY IN SINDARIN]: We need your protection.
(Boe ammen veriad lîn.)
The road is fell!
(Andelu i ven!)
I'm glad we came to you.
(Merin le telim.)
We need your support!
(Boe ammen i dulu lîn!)
HALDIR:
Aragorn...
HALDIR:  ...Eärendil.
(...Eärendil.)
ARAGORN:  I'm glad we came to you.
(Merin le telim.)
The road is too dangerous.
(Andelu i ven.)
[SINGING IN SINDARIN] The bonds cut,
(In gwidh ristennin,)
[CHORUS IN QUENYA] Our regret is undying
(Ilfirin nairelma)
the spirit rent (i fae narchannen)
[CHORUS] What should be... (Nauva i...)
The Flame of Anor (I lach Anor ed)
[CHORUS] shall be. (...nauva.)
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying (Ilfirin nairelma)
from earth departed (ardhon gwannen)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
Mithrandir, (Mithrandir,)
O Pilgrim Grey (A Randir Vithren)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
You will not wander... (Ú-reniathach...)
[CHORUS] What should be shall be. (Nauva i nauva.)
the world green (i amar galen)
[CHORUS] Love... (Melme...)
[CHORUS] ...for this land... (...nóren sina...)
Your journey in... (I reniad lín ne...)
[CHORUS] is our lament. (nairelma.)
darkness, ended (môr, nuithannen.)
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying
(Ilfirin nairelma)
[CHORUS] Is deeper than the sea's...
(Núra lá earo...)
[CHORUS] ...depths
(...núri)
[IN SINDARIN] (Le aphadar aen.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Am meleth dîn,)
I ant e guil Arwen Undómiel pígatha.
[IN SINDARIN] (Aníron i e broniatha ad ae periatham,)
(athar i methid en-amar hen.)
(Aníron i e círatha na Valannor.)
[IN QUENYA] (Namárië.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Nadath nâ i moe cerich.)
But...
(Dan...)
(Ú-'eveditham...)
(Elessar.)
VOICE OF THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  Here...
(Akha...)
VOICE OF THE RING:  ...only death.
(...ashi gurum.)
[v1.6]