ELROND [IN SINDARIN]: (Anirne hene beriad i chên lîn...)
(ned Imladris nauthant e le beriathar aen.)
[IN ENGLISH] In her heart, your mother
knew you'd be hunted all your life.
That you'd never escape your fate.
The skill of the Elves
can reforge the sword of kings...
...but only you have the power
to wield it.
I do not want that power.
I have never wanted it.
You are the last of that bloodline.
There is no other.
BILBO:
My old sword! Sting.
Here, take it. Take it.
-It's so light.
-Yes. Made by the Elves, you know.
The blade glows blue
when Orcs are close.
And it's times like that, my lad,
when you have to be extra careful.
Here's a pretty thing.
Mithril.
As light as a feather,
and as hard as dragon scales.
Let me see you put it on. Come on.
Oh!
My old ring.
I should very much like...
...to hold it again, one last time.
I'm sorry I brought this upon you,
my boy.
I'm sorry that you
must carry this burden.
I'm sorry for everything.
The Ring-bearer is setting out
on the Quest of Mount Doom.
On you who travel with him,
no oath...
...nor bond is laid to go further
than you will.
Farewell. Hold to your purpose.
May the blessings of Elves and Men...
...and all Free Folk go with you.
The Fellowship awaits the Ring-bearer.
Mordor, Gandalf, is it left or right?
Left.
GANDALF:  We must hold to this course,
west of the Misty Mountains, for 40 days.
If our luck holds, the Gap of Rohan
will still be open to us.
From there, our road
turns east to Mordor.
Two, one, five. Good! Very good.
Move your feet.
MERRY: You look good, Pippin.
-Thanks.
BOROMIR:
Faster!
If anyone was to ask for my opinion,
which I note they're not...
...I'd say we were taking
the long way 'round.
Gandalf, we could pass through
the Mines of Moria.
My cousin Balin would give us
a royal welcome.
No, I would not take the road through
Moria unless I had no other choice.
Sorry!
MERRY:
Get him!
MERRY: For the Shire!
PIPPIN: Hold him. Hold him down, Merry!
Gentlemen, that's enough.
MERRY: You've got my arm!
You've got my arm!
-What is that?
-Nothing. It's just a wisp of cloud.
It's moving fast.
Against the wind.
-Crebain from Dunland!
-Hide!
-Hurry!
-Take cover!
Spies of Saruman.
The passage south is being watched.
We must take the Pass of Caradhras.
ARAGORN:
Frodo!
Boromir.
It is a strange fate that we should
suffer so much fear and doubt...
...over so small a thing.
Such a little thing.
Boromir!
Give the Ring to Frodo.
As you wish.
I care not.
[BOROMIR CHUCKLES]
[BIRDS SQUAWKING]
So, Gandalf, you try
to lead them over Caradhras.
And if that fails,
where then will you go?
If the mountain defeats you...
...will you risk
a more dangerous road?
[SARUMAN CHANTS IN QUENYA]
There is a fell voice on the air.
It's Saruman!
He's trying to bring down the mountain!
Gandalf, we must turn back!
No!
[CHANTS IN SINDARIN] Sleep Caradhras, be still, lie still...
(Losto Caradhras, sedho, hodo...
...hold [your wrath]!
(...nuitho [i 'ruith!])
SARUMAN [CHANTS IN QUENYA]:  Wake up cruel Redhorn!
(Cuiva nwalca Carnirassë!)
May your blood-stained horn...
(Nai yarvaxëa rasselya...)
...shall fall upon the enemy-heads!
(...taltuva ñotto-carinnar!)
Wake up cruel...
(Cuiva nwalca...)
...Redhorn!
(...Carnirassë!)
We must get off the mountain!
Make for the Gap of Rohan,
and take the west road to my city!
The Gap of Rohan takes us
too close to Isengard!
GIMLI: We cannot pass over a mountain.
Let us go under it.
Let us go through the Mines of Moria.
SARUMAN:  Moria. You fear to go
into those mines.
The Dwarves delved too greedily
and too deep.
You know what they awoke
in the darkness of Khazad-dûm:
Shadow and flame.
Let the Ring-bearer decide.
We cannot stay here!
This will be the death of the Hobbits.
Frodo?
We will go through the mines.
So be it.
Frodo, come and help an old man.
How is your shoulder?
-Better than it was.
-And the Ring?
You feel its power growing, don't you?
I've felt it too.
You must be careful now.
Evil will be drawn to you
from outside the Fellowship.
And, I fear, from within.
-Who then do I trust?
-You must trust yourself.
Trust your own strengths.
-What do you mean?
-There are many powers in this world...
...for good or for evil.
Some are greater than I am.
And against some I have not yet
been tested.
The walls...
...of Moria.
Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
GANDALF: Yes Gimli, their own masters cannot find
them if their secrets are forgotten.
Why doesn't that surprise me?
Well, let's see.
Ithildin.
It mirrors only starlight
and moonlight.
It reads, "The Doors of Durin,
Lord of Moria.
-Speak, friend, and enter."
-What do you suppose that means?
It's simple. If you are a friend, you speak
the password and the doors will open.
[IN SINDARIN] Gate of the Elves, open now for me!
(Annon Edhellen, edro hi ammen.)
Doorway of the Dwarf-folk, listen to the word of my tongue.
(Fennas Nogothrim, lasto beth lammen.)
Nothing's happening.
I once knew every spell
in all the tongues of Elves...
...Men and Orcs.
What are you going to do, then?
Knock your head against these doors,
Peregrin Took!
And if that does not shatter them...
...and I am allowed a little peace
from foolish questions...
...I will try to find the opening words.
[GANDALF SPEAKS IN DWARVISH]
[IN SINDARIN] Gate of Elves...
(Ando Eldarinwa...)
...listen to my word,
(...a lasta quettanya,)
Threshold of Dwarves!
(Fenda Casarinwa!)
Mines are no place for a pony.
-Even one so brave as Bill.
-Bye-bye, Bill.
Go on, Bill. Go on.
Don't worry, Sam,
he knows the way home.
Do not disturb the water.
Oh, it's useless.
It's a riddle.
"Speak 'friend' and enter."
What's the Elvish word for "friend"?
Mellon.
GIMLI: Soon, Master Elf, you will enjoy
the fabled hospitality of the Dwarves.
Roaring fires, malt beer,
ripe meat off the bone!
This, my friend,
is the home of my cousin Balin.
And they call it a mine.
A mine!
This is no mine. It's a tomb.
GIMLI:
No.
No...
No!
Goblins.
We make for the Gap of Rohan.
We should never have come here.
ARAGORN:
Now, get out of here. Get out!
MERRY: Frodo!
FRODO: Help!
Strider!
SAM: Get off him!
Aragorn!
Frodo!
Strider!
Into the mines!
-Legolas!
ARAGORN: Into the cave!
Run!
GANDALF:
We now have but one choice.
We must face the long dark of Moria.
Be on your guard.
There are older
and fouler things than Orcs...
...in the deep places of the world.
Quietly now. It's a four-day journey
to the other side.
Let us hope that our presence
may go unnoticed.
The wealth of Moria is not in gold...
...or jewels...
...but mithril.
Bilbo had a shirt of mithril rings
that Thorin gave him.
-Oh, that was a kingly gift.
-Yes.
I never told him...
...but its worth was greater than
the value of the Shire.
Pippin.
I have no memory of this place.
PIPPIN: Are we lost?
MERRY: No.
PIPPIN: I think we are.
MERRY: Gandalf's thinking.
PIPPIN: Merry?
MERRY: What?
PIPPIN:
I'm hungry.
-There's something down there.
-It's Gollum.
-Gollum?
-He's been following us for three days.
-He escaped the dungeons of Barad-dûr?
-Escaped...
...or was set loose.
Now the Ring has brought him here.
He will never be rid of his need for it.
He hates and loves the Ring,
as he hates and loves himself.
Sméagol's life is a sad story.
Yes, Sméagol he was once called.
Before the Ring found him.
Before it drove him mad.
It's a pity Bilbo didn't kill him
when he had the chance.
Pity?
It is pity that stayed Bilbo's hand.
Many that live deserve death.
Some that die deserve life.
Can you give it to them, Frodo?
Do not be too eager
to deal out death and judgment.
Even the very wise
cannot see all ends.
My heart tells me that Gollum has some
part to play yet, for good or ill...
...before this is over.
The pity of Bilbo
may rule the fate of many.
I wish the Ring
had never come to me.
I wish none of this had happened.
So do all who live to see such times.
But that is not for them to decide.
All we have to decide is what to do
with the time that is given to us.
There are other forces at work in this
world, Frodo, besides the will of evil.
Bilbo was meant to find the Ring.
In which case,
you also were meant to have it.
And that is an encouraging thought.
Ah!
It's that way.
-He's remembered.
GANDALF: No.
But the air doesn't smell
so foul down here.
If in doubt, Meriadoc,
always follow your nose.
Let me risk a little more light.
Behold...
...the great realm
and Dwarf-city of Dwarrowdelf.
There's an eye opener, and no mistake.
Gimli!
No.
No!
Oh, no.
No.
GANDALF:
"Here lies Balin...
...son of Fundin...
...Lord of Moria."
He is dead, then.
It's as I feared.
GIMLI [IN KHUZDÛL]:
(Kheled-zâram... Balin tazlifi.)
We must move on. We cannot linger.
GANDALF: "They have taken the bridge
and the second hall.
We have barred the gates...
...but cannot hold them for long.
The ground shakes.
Drums...
...drums in the deep.
We cannot get out.
A Shadow moves in the dark.
They are coming."
[CLATTERING]
[THUDDING]
[SILENCE]
Fool of a Took!
Throw yourself in next time,
and rid us of your stupidity.
[DRUMS BEATING]
[SCREECHING]
SAM:
Frodo!
Orcs.
Get back! Stay close to Gandalf!
They have a cave-troll.
Let them come!
There is one Dwarf yet in Moria
who still draws breath.
[SCREECHES]
I think I'm getting the hang of this.
Frodo!
FRODO:
Aragorn! Aragorn!
Frodo!
Oh, no.
[FRODO GROANS]
He's alive.
I'm all right. I'm not hurt.
You should be dead.
That spear would have skewered
a wild boar.
I think there's more to this Hobbit
than meets the eye.
Mithril.
You are full of surprises,
Master Baggins.
[SCREECHING]
To the Bridge of Khazad-dûm!
ARAGORN:
This way!
[GROWLING]
What is this new devilry?
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
A Balrog.
A demon of the ancient world.
This foe is beyond any of you.
Run!
Quickly!
Gandalf.
Lead them on, Aragorn.
The bridge is near.
[BALROG GROWLS]
Do as I say!
Swords are no more use here.
Gandalf!
BOROMIR:
Merry! Pippin!
Sam!
Nobody tosses a Dwarf.
Not the beard!
Steady.
Hold on!
[BALROG GROWLS]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
Hang on!
Lean forward!
Steady.
Come on!
Now!
Over the bridge!
Fly!
You cannot pass!
Gandalf!
I am a servant of the Secret Fire,
wielder of the flame of Anor.
The dark fire will not avail you,
flame of Udûn!
Go back to the Shadow.
You shall not pass!
BOROMIR: No! No!
-Gandalf!
Fly, you fools!
No!
Aragorn!
Legolas, get them up.
Give them a moment, for pity's sake!
By nightfall, these hills will
be swarming with Orcs.
We must reach the woods of Lothlórien.
Come, Boromir. Legolas.
Gimli, get them up.
On your feet, Sam.
Frodo?
Frodo!
Stay close, young Hobbits!
They say that a great sorceress
lives in these woods.
An Elf-witch...
...of terrible power.
All who look upon her...
...fall under her spell.
GALADRIEL:
Frodo!
And are never seen again.
GALADRIEL:  Your coming to us is
as the footsteps of doom.
You bring great evil here,
Ring-bearer.
SAM:
Mr. Frodo?
Well, here's one Dwarf
she won't ensnare so easily.
I have the eyes of a hawk
and the ears of a fox.
The Dwarf breathes so loud,
we could have shot him in the dark.
[IN SINDARIN] (Mae govannen, Legolas Thranduilion.)
(Govannas vîn gwennen le, Haldir o Lórien.)
(A Aragorn in Dúnedain...)
(istannen le ammen.)
Haldir.
So much for the legendary courtesy
of the Elves!
Speak words we can all understand!
[IN ENGLISH] We have not had dealings
with the Dwarves since the Dark Days.
And you know what this Dwarf
says to that?
[IN KHUZDÛL] I spit upon your grave.
(Ishkhaqwi ai durugnul.)
That was not so courteous.
You bring great evil with you.
You can go no further.
ARAGORN [URGENTLY IN SINDARIN]: We need your protection.
(Boe ammen veriad lîn.)
The road is fell!
(Andelu i ven!)
I'm glad we came to you.
(Merin le telim.)
We need your support!
(Boe ammen i dulu lîn!)
HALDIR:
Aragorn...
(...Eärendil.)
I'm glad we came to you.
(Merin le telim.)
The road is too dangerous.
(Andelu i ven.)
Gandalf's death was not in vain.
Nor would he have you give up hope.
You carry a heavy burden, Frodo.
Don't carry the weight of the dead.
You will follow me.
Caras Galadhon.
The heart of Elvendom on earth.
Realm of the Lord Celeborn
and of Galadriel, Lady of Light.
The enemy knows you have entered here.
What hope you had in secrecy
is now gone.
Eight there are here, yet nine there
were set out from Rivendell.
Tell me, where is Gandalf?
For I much desire to speak with him.
I can no longer see him from afar.
GALADRIEL: Gandalf the Grey did not
pass the borders of this land.
He has fallen into Shadow.
He was taken by both Shadow and flame.
A Balrog of Morgoth.
For we went needlessly
into the net of Moria.
Needless were none of the deeds
of Gandalf in life.
We do not yet know his full purpose.
Do not let the great emptiness
of Khazad-dûm fill your heart...
...Gimli, son of Glóin.
For the world has grown
full of peril...
...and in all lands...
...love is now mingled with grief.
What now becomes of this Fellowship?
Without Gandalf, hope is lost.
The quest stands upon the edge
of a knife.
Stray but a little and it will fail...
...to the ruin of all.
Yet hope remains
while the Company is true.
Do not let your hearts be troubled.
Go now and rest...
...for you are weary with sorrow
and much toil.
Tonight, you will sleep...
GALADRIEL:
Welcome, Frodo of the Shire...
...one who has seen the Eye!
[SINGING IN SINDARIN] The bonds cut,
(In gwidh ristennin,)
[CHORUS IN QUENYA] Our regret is undying
(Ilfirin nairelma)
the spirit... (i fae...)
A lament for Gandalf.
...rent (...narchannen)
[CHORUS] What should be... (Nauva i...)
What do they say about him?
I have not the heart to tell you.
The Flame of Anor (I lach Anor ed)
[CHORUS] shall be. (...nauva.)
For me, the grief is still too near.
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying (Ilfirin nairelma)
I bet they don't mention his fireworks.
from earth... (ardhon...)
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying (Ilfirin nairelma)
There should be a verse about them.
...departed (...gwannen)
[CHORUS] Our regret is undying (Ilfirin nairelma)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
The finest rockets ever seen
Mith- (Mith-)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
They burst in stars of blue and green
-randir, (-randir,)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
SAM:
Or after thunder,
O Pilgrim Grey (A Randir Vithren)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
SAM:
silver showers
O Pilgrim Grey (A Randir Vithren)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
SAM:
Came falling like a rain of flowers
Oh, that doesn't do them justice
by a long road.
You will not wander... (Ú-reniathach...)
[CHORUS] Rather than submit (Ar ullume nucuvalme)
[CHORUS] What should be shall be. (Nauva i nauva.)
the world... (i amar...)
[CHORUS] Love... (Melme...)
ARAGORN:
Take some rest.
...green (...galen)
[CHORUS] Love... (Melme...)
These borders are well-protected.
I will find no rest here.
[CHORUS] ...for this land... (...nóren sina...)
[Your]... (I...)
I heard her voice inside my head.
journey in... (...reniad lín ne...)
[CHORUS] is our lament. (nairelma.)
She spoke of my father
and the fall of Gondor.
darkness, ended (môr, nuithannen.)
[CHORUS] is our lament. (nairelma.)
She said to me,
"Even now there is hope left."
[CHORUS] Undying...
(Ilfirin...)
But I cannot see it.
[CHORUS] ...is our regret
(...nairelma)
It is long since we had any hope.
[CHORUS] Is deeper than the sea's...
(Núra lá earo...)
[CHORUS] ...depths
(...núri)
My father is a noble man.
But his rule is failing...
...and our people lose faith.
He looks to me to make things right,
and I would do it.
I would see the glory
of Gondor restored.
Have you ever seen it, Aragorn?
The White Tower of Ecthelion.
Glimmering like a spike
of pearl and silver.
Its banners caught high
in the morning breeze.
Have you ever been called home...
...by the clear ringing
of silver trumpets?
I have seen the White City...
...long ago.
One day, our paths will lead us there.
And the tower guard
shall take up the call:
"The Lords of Gondor have returned."
Will you look into the mirror?
What will I see?
Even the wisest cannot tell.
For the mirror...
...shows many things.
Things that were...
...things that are...
...and some things...
...that have not yet come to pass.
[VOICES SPEAKING IN BLACK SPEECH]
I know what it is you saw.
For it is also in my mind.
It is what will come to pass
if you should fail.
The Fellowship is breaking.
It is already begun.
He will try to take the Ring.
You know of whom I speak.
One by one, it will destroy them all.
FRODO:
If you ask it of me...
...I will give you the One Ring.
You offer it to me freely.
I do not deny that my heart
has greatly desired this.
In place of a Dark Lord,
you would have a queen...
...not dark but beautiful,
and terrible as the dawn!
Treacherous as the seal
Stronger than the foundations
of the earth!
All shall love me...
...and despair.
I pass the test. I will diminish...
...and go into the West...
-...and remain Galadriel.
- cannot do this alone.
You are a Ring-bearer, Frodo.
To bear a Ring of Power...
...Is to be alone.
This is Nenya,
the Ring of Adamant.
And I am its keeper.
This task was appointed to you.
And if you do not find a way...
...no one will.
Then I know what I must do.
It's just...
...I'm afraid to do it.
Even the smallest person can change
the course of the future.
Do you know how the Orcs
first came into being?
They were Elves once.
Taken by the Dark Powers...
...tortured and mutilated.
A ruined and terrible form of life.
And now...
...perfected.
My fighting Uruk-hai...
...whom do you serve?
Saruman!
Hunt them down. Do not stop
until they are found.
You do not know pain.
You do not know fear.
You will taste Man-flesh!
One of the halflings carries
something of great value.
Bring them to me alive and unspoiled.
Kill the others.
CELEBORN: Never before have we clad
strangers in the garb of our own people.
May these cloaks help shield you
from unfriendly eyes.
Lembas.
Elvish waybread.
One small bite is enough to fill
the stomach of a grown man.
How many did you eat?
Four.
[BELCHES]
CELEBORN:  Every league you travel south,
the danger will increase.
Mordor Orcs now hold the eastern shore
of the Anduin.
Nor will you find safety
on the western bank.
Strange creatures bearing the White Hand
have been seen on our borders.
Seldom do Orcs journey in the open
under the sun, yet these have done so.
[IN SINDARIN] (Le aphadar aen.)
[IN ENGLISH]
By river you have the chance...
...of outrunning the enemy
to the Falls of Rauros.
GALADRIEL: My gift for you, Legolas,
is a bow of the Galadhrim.
Worthy of the skill
of our woodland kin.
These are the daggers of the Noldorin.
They have already seen service in war.
Do not fear, young Peregrin Took.
You will find your courage.
And for you, Samwise Gamgee...
...Elven rope made of hithlain.
Thank you, my lady.
Have you run out
of those nice, shiny daggers?
And what gift would a dwarf ask
of the Elves?
Nothing.
Except to look upon the lady
of the Galadhrim one last time...
...for she is more fair
than all the jewels beneath the earth.
Actually...
There was one thing.
No, no, I'm talking nonsense.
It's quite impossible.
Stupid to ask.
GALADRIEL:
I have nothing greater to give...
...than the gift you already bear.
[IN SINDARIN] (Am meleth dîn,)
I ant e guil Arwen Undómiel pígatha.
[IN SINDARIN] (Aníron i e broniatha ad ae periatham,)
(athar i methid en-amar hen.)
(Aníron i e círatha na Valannor.)
[IN ENGLISH]
That choice is yet before her.
You have your own choice to make,
Aragorn.
To rise above the height of all
your fathers since the days of Elendil...
...or to fall into darkness
with all that is left of your kin.
[IN QUENYA] (Namárië.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Nadath nâ i moe cerich.)
But...
(Dan...)
(Ú-'eveditham...)
(Elessar.)
[IN ENGLISH]
Farewell, Frodo Baggins.
I give you the light of Eärendil...
...our most beloved star.
May it be a light for you
in dark places...
...when all other lights go out.
GIMLI: I have taken my worst wound
at this parting...
...having looked my last upon that
which is fairest.
Henceforth I will call nothing fair
unless it be her gift to me.
What was her gift?
I asked her for one hair
from her golden head.
She gave me three.
[BIRDS SQUAWKING]
Gollum. He has tracked us since Moria.
I had hoped we would lose him
on the river.
But he's too clever a waterman.
And if he alerts the enemy
to our whereabouts...
...it will make the crossing
even more dangerous.
SAM:
Have some food, Mr. Frodo.
-No, Sam.
-You haven't eaten anything all day.
You're not sleeping, neither.
Don't think I haven't noticed.
-Mr. Frodo--
-I'm all right.
But you're not.
I'm here to help you.
I promised Gandalf that I would.
You can't help me, Sam.
Not this time.
Get some sleep.
Minas Tirith is the safer road.
You know that.
From there we can regroup.
Strike out for Mordor from a place
of strength.
There is no strength in Gondor
that can avail us.
You were quick enough to trust
the Elves.
Have you so little faith
in your own people?
Yes, there is weakness.
There is frailty.
But there is courage also,
and honor to be found in Men.
But you will not see that.
You are afraid!
All your life, you have hidden
in the shadows.
Scared of who you are,
of what you are.
I will not lead the Ring within
a hundred leagues of your city.
Frodo.
The Argonath.
Long have I desired
to look upon the kings of old.
My kin.
We cross the lake at nightfall.
Hide the boats and continue on foot.
-We approach Mordor from the North.
-Oh, yes?
Just a simple matter of finding
our way through Emyn Muil...
...an impassable labyrinth
of razor-sharp rocks.
And after that, it gets even better.
Festering, stinking marshland
as far as the eye can see.
That is our road.
I suggest you take some rest
and recover your strength, Master Dwarf.
Recover my--
-We should leave now.
-No.
Orcs patrol the eastern shore.
We must wait for cover of darkness.
It is not the eastern shore
that worries me.
A shadow and a threat
has been growing in my mind.
Something draws near.
I can feel it.
Recover strength?
Pay no heed to that, young Hobbit.
Where's Frodo?
BOROMIR:
None of us should wander alone.
You, least of all.
So much depends on you.
Frodo?
I know why you seek solitude.
You suffer. I see it day by day.
You sure you do not suffer needlessly?
There are other ways, Frodo.
-Other paths that we might take.
-I know what you would say.
It would seem like wisdom
but for the warning in my heart.
Warning? Against what?
We're all afraid, Frodo.
But to let that fear drive us,
to destroy what hope we have...
-...don't you see that is madness?
-There is no other way.
I ask only for the strength
to defend my people!
-If you would but lend me the Ring.
-No.
-Why do you recoil? I am no thief.
-You are not yourself.
What chance do you think you have?
They will find you.
They will take the Ring.
And you will beg for death
before the end!
You fool!
It is not yours, save by unhappy chance!
It could have been mine.
It should be mine! Give it to me!
-Give it to me!
-No!
-No.
I see your mind.
You will take the Ring to Sauron!
You will betray us!
You'll go to your death,
and the death of us all!
Curse you!
Curse you and all the halflings!
Frodo?
Frodo.
What have I done?
Please, Frodo.
Frodo, I'm sorry!
Frodo!
[VOICE OF THE RING
SPEAKS IN BLACK SPEECH]
VOICE OF THE RING:  They will fall.
(A'ghi gûr'ruzh.)
Frodo?
-It has taken Boromir.
-Where is the Ring?
Stay away!
Frodo!
-I swore to protect you.
-Can you protect me from yourself?
Would you destroy it?
VOICE OF THE RING:
Aragorn.
Elessar.
I would have gone with you to the end.
Into the very fires of Mordor.
I know.
Look after the others. Especially Sam.
He will not understand.
Go, Frodo!
Run.
Run!
Mr. Frodo!
Find the halfling!
Elendil!
Aragorn, go!
PIPPIN:
Frodo!
Hide here. Quick!
Come on!
What's he doing?
He's leaving.
-No!
-Pippin!
MERRY:
Run, Frodo. Go on!
-Hey! Hey, you!
-Over here!
-This way!
-It's working!
-I know it's working! Run!
[HORN BLOWS]
-The horn of Gondor.
-Boromir.
Run!
[ARROW HITS]
No.
-They took the little ones.
-Hold still.
Frodo. Where is Frodo?
I let Frodo go.
Then you did what I could not.
I tried to take the Ring from him.
-The Ring is beyond our reach now.
-Forgive me.
I did not see it.
-I have failed you all.
-No, Boromir.
You fought bravely.
You have kept your honor.
BOROMIR:
Leave it.
It is over.
The world of Men will fall.
And all will come to darkness...
...and my city to ruin.
I do not know what strength
is in my blood...
...but I swear to you,
I will not let the White City fall...
...nor our people fail.
Our people.
I would have followed you, my brother.
My captain.
My king.
Be at peace...
...son of Gondor.
They will look for his coming
from the White Tower.
But he will not return.
Frodo!
FRODO:
I wish the Ring had never come to me.
I wish none of this had happened.
GANDALF:  So do all who live
to see such times...
...but that is not for them to decide.
All you have to decide...
...is what to do with the time
that is given to you.
Frodo, no!
Frodo!
-Mr. Frodo!
-No, Sam.
Go back, Sam!
-I'm going to Mordor alone.
-Of course you are.
And I'm coming with you!
You can't swim!
Sam!
I made a promise, Mr. Frodo.
A promise:
"Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."
And I don't mean to.
I don't mean to.
Sam.
Come on.
Hurry! Frodo and Sam
have reached the eastern shore.
-You mean not to follow them.
-Frodo's fate is no longer in our hands.
Then it has all been in vain.
The Fellowship has failed.
Not if we hold true to each other.
We will not abandon Merry and Pippin
to torment and death.
Not while we have strength left.
Leave all that can be spared behind.
We travel light.
Let us hunt some Orc.
Yes!
FRODO:
Mordor.
I hope the others find a safer road.
Strider will look after them.
I don't suppose
we'll ever see them again.
We may yet, Mr. Frodo.
We may.
Sam...
...I'm glad you are with me.
[English & Sindarin & Quenya - US - SDH - v1.3]