GALADRIEL [IN SINDARIN]:
(I amar prestar aen.)
(Han mathon ne nen.)
(Han mathon ne chae.)
(A han noston ned 'wilith.)
[IN SINDARIN] Hold positions!
(Tangado haid!)
Release the arrows!
(Leithio i philinn!)
Positions!
(Haid!)
VOICE OF THE RING [WHISPERS IN BLACK SPEECH]:  Sauron...
(Zigur...)
[SINGING IN SINDARIN]  O Queen beyond the Western Seas!
(A Bereth thar Ennui Aeair!)
O light to us that wander
(Calad ammen i reniar)
Amid the tree-woven lands of Middle-earth.
(Mi 'aladhremmin ennorath.)
O Elbereth Star-kindler
(A Elbereth Gilthoniel)
your eyes and breath like shining jewels...
(i chin a thûl lín míriel...)
STRIDER [HUMS IN SINDARIN]:  Tinúviel the elven-fair
(Tinúviel elvanui)
Immortal maiden...
(Elleth alfirin...)
...elven-wise
(...edhelhael)
About him cast her night-dark hair
(O hon ring finnil fuinui)
And arms like silver...
(A renc gelebrin...)
VOICE OF THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  In the void...
(Gûm-ishi...)
Only...
(Ashi...)
Death...
(Gurum...)
VOICE OF THE RING:  Where the Shadows lie...
(Makha Gulshu darulu...)
In the Land of Mordor where Shadows lie.
(Daghburz-ishi makha Gulshu darulu.)
[SINGING IN QUENYA]  The earth groans
(I cemen nurrua)
And the wind...
(Ar i sure...)
...the wind...
(...i súre...)
...is crying!
(...naina!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Im Arwen - telin le thaed.)
(Lasto beth nîn...)
(Tolo dan nan galad.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Dartho guin Beriain - rych le ad tolthathon.)
(Hon mabathon - rochon ellint im.)
(Andelu i ven.)
ARWEN: [Frodo is dying.] (Frodo fîr. Ae athradon i hîr...)
(...tûr gwaith nîn beriatha hon.)
[IN SINDARIN] As you wish.
(Be iest lîn.)
[IN SINDARIN] Ride fast, Asfaloth, ride fast!
(Noro lim, Asfaloth, noro lim!)
Ride fast, Asfaloth!
(Noro lim, Asfaloth!)
[IN SINDARIN] Waters of the Misty Mountains, listen to the great word;
(Nîn o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer;)
flow waters of Loudwater, against the Ringwraiths!
(rimmo nîn Bruinen, dan in Ulaer!)
Waters of the Misty Mountains, listen to the great word;
(Nîn o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer;)
flow waters of Loudwater, against the Ringwraiths!
(rimmo nîn Bruinen, dan in Ulaer!)
[IN SINDARIN] Hear my voice. Come back to the light.
(Lasto beth nîn. Tolo dan nan galad.)
[IN SINDARIN] (A si i-Dhúath ú-orthor, Aragorn.)
(Ú or le... a ú or nin.)
(Renich i lú i erui govannem?)
(Nauthannen i ned ôl reniannen.)
(Gwenwin in enninath.)
(Ú-'arnech in naeth i si celich.)
(Renich i beth i pennen?)
THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  In the cold...
(Kelkum-ishi...)
[CHANTS IN BLACK SPEECH] One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
...One Ring to bring them all...
(...Ash Nazg thrakatulûk...)
...and in the darkness bind them.
(...agh burzum-ishi krimpatul.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Havo dad, Legolas.)
THE RING:  In the Land of Mordor where...
(Daghburz-ishi makha...)
...your blood.
(...sherkuk.)
THE RING:  Where the Shadows lie...
(Makha Gulshu darulu...)
THE RING:  One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
One Ring to rule them all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)