[IN SINDARIN] May they find peace after death.
(Hiro hyn hîdh ab 'wanath.)
(Aragorn, nad no ennas!)
(Man cenich?)
[IN ROHIRRIC] An evil death has set...
(Bealocwealm hafað fréone...)
...forth the noble warrior.
(...frecan forth onsended.)
A song shall sing...
(Giedd sculon singan...)
...sorrowing minstrels.
(...gléomenn sorgiende.)
In Meduseld...
(On Meduselde...)
...that he is no more...
(...þæt he ma no wære...)
...for his necessary rest.
(...is þurh niedig rest.)
And that he is the dearest kinsman...
(And mægen deorost...)
...killing took him...
(...bealo...)
[IN ROHIRRIC] Be thou well.
(Westu hál.)
Go thou, Théodred, go thou.
(Ferðu, Théodred, Ferðu.)
ARAGORN [IN ROHIRRIC]: Fast...
(Fæste...)
...quiet now.
(...stille nú.)
Fast...
(Fæste...)
Quiet...
(Stille...)
...quiet...
(...stille...)
A battle is stirring, you heard
(Lac is drefed, gefrægon..)
What is your name?
(Hwæt nemnað ðe?)
(Ðin nama is cynglic.)
ARAGORN [IN SINDARIN]:  What troubles you, Brego?
(Man le trasta, Brego?)
What did you see?
(Man cenich?)