[IN SINDARIN] May they find peace after death.
(Hiro hyn hîdh ab 'wanath.)
(Aragorn, nad no ennas!)
(Man cenich?)
[IN ROHIRRIC] An evil death has set...
(Bealocwealm hafað fréone...)
...forth the noble warrior.
(...frecan forth onsended.)
A song shall sing...
(Giedd sculon singan...)
...sorrowing minstrels.
(...gléomenn sorgiende.)
In Meduseld...
(On Meduselde...)
...that he is no more...
(...þæt he ma no wære...)
...for his necessary rest.
(...is þurh niedig rest.)
And that he is the dearest kinsman...
(And mægen deorost...)
...killing took him...
(...bealo...)
[IN ROHIRRIC] Be thou well.
(Westu hál.)
Go thou, Théodred, go thou.
(Ferðu, Théodred, Ferðu.)
ARAGORN [IN ROHIRRIC]: Fast...
(Fæste...)
...quiet now.
(...stille nú.)
Fast...
(Fæste...)
Quiet...
(Stille...)
...quiet...
(...stille...)
A battle is stirring, you heard
(Lac is drefed, gefrægon..)
What is your name?
(Hwæt nemnað ðe?)
(Ðin nama is cynglic.)
ARAGORN [IN SINDARIN]:  What troubles you, Brego?
(Man le trasta, Brego?)
What did you see?
(Man cenich?)
[IN SINDARIN] (Minlû pedich nin...)
(i aur hen telitha.)
(Ú i vethed... nâ i onnad.)
(Boe bedich go Frodo.)
(Han bâd lîn.)
(Dolen i vâd o nin.)
(Si peliannen i vâd na dail lîn.)
(Si boe ú-dhannathach.)
(Ae ú-esteliach nad...)
(estelio han...)
(estelio ammen.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Nach gwannatha sin?)
(Ma nathach hi gwannathach or minuial - archened?)
[IN SINDARIN] (Ú-ethelithon.)
(Estelio guru lîn ne dagor.)
(Ethelithach.)
(Ú-bedin o gurth ne dagor.)
(O man pedich?)
(Edra le men...)
(...men na guil edwen...)
(haer o auth...a nîr...a naeth.)
[URUK-HAI CHANTING IN BLACK SPEECH]: Lord of the Ring!
(Durbgu nazgshu!)
Lord of the Earth!
(Durbgu dashshu!)
Lord of the Ring!
(Durbgu nazgshu!)
Lord of the Earth!
(Durbgu dashshu!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Tollen i lû.)
(I chair gwannar na Valannor. Si bado... no círar.)
[IN SINDARIN] (A im ú-'erin veleth lîn?)
(Gerich meleth nîn, ada.)
GALADRIEL [IN SINDARIN]:  The world is changed.
(I amar prestar aen.)
I feel it in the water,
(Han mathon ne nen,)
I feel it in the earth,
(han mathon ne chae,)
and I smell it in...
(a han noston ned...)
...the air.
(...'wilith.)
[IN SINDARIN] Well done, Brego, my friend.
(Mae carnen, Brego, mellon nîn.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Le abdollen.)
[IN SINDARIN] Thank you.
(Hannon le.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Boe a hyn...)
(Neled herain...                            )
(Neled herain... dan caer menig!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Si beriathar hyn ammaeg na ned Edoras...)
Aragorn.
(Nedin dagor hen ú-'erir ortheri.)
(Natha daged dhaer!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Ú-moe edhored, Legolas.)
Well met, Haldir!
(Mae govannen, Haldir!)
[IN SINDARIN] O, Children of Eru... (A Eruchîn...)
...show them no mercy... (...ú-dano i faelas a hyn...)
(an uben tanatha le faelas!)
(Dartho!)
(Tangado a chadad!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Faeg i-varv...dîn na lanc...)
(...a nu ranc.)
(Leithio i philinn!)
Release arrows!
(Hado i philinn!)
(Pendraith!)
[IN SINDARIN] Causeway!
(Na fennas!)
Shoot continuously!
(Hado ribed!)
Throw!
(Hado!)
(Togo han dad, Legolas!)
(Dago hon!)
Hurl the arrows!
(Hado i philinn!)
(Herio!)
[IN SINDARIN] (Nan Barad!)
To the Keep! (Nan Barad!)
[IN SINDARIN] To the Keep!
(Nan Barad!)
[v1.2]