[IN QUENYA] Hail Eärendil brightest of the Stars!
(Aiya Eärendil Elenion Ancalima!)
SAURON [IN SINDARIN]: White-glittering slants down...
(Silivren penna míriel...)
SAURON: ...sparkling like jewels!
(...o menel aglar elenath!)
White-glittering slants down...
(Silivren penna míriel...)
SAURON [IN BLACK SPEECH]:
(Ombi kur gundum-ishi...)
And in darkness bind them.
(Agh burzum-ishi krimpatul.)
ARAGORN [IN QUENYA]:  Out of the Great Sea...
(Et Eärello...)
...to Middle-earth I am come.
(...Endorenna utúlien.)
In this place will I abide...
(Sinomë maruvan...)
...and my heirs...
(...ar Hildinyar...)
...unto the ending of the world.
(...tenn' Ambar-metta.)
[IN SINDARIN] Thank you.
(Hannon le.)
[IN SINDARIN] (I Aear cân ven na mar.)