VOICE OF THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  ...them all...
(...batulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
[IN ROHIRRIC] Be-thou Aragorn well.
(Westu Aragorn hál.)
SAURON [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  Bring the One Ring.
Ash nazg thrakatum.
[IN SINDARIN] Father...
(Ada...)
Father...
[IN SINDARIN] (Ónen i-Estel Edain.)
[IN SINDARIN] (Ú-chebin Estel anim.)
[ORC CALL IN BLACK SPEECH]: Death! (Gurut!)
[ORCS CHANTING]: To war! (Kutmuda!)
Death! (Gurut!)
To war! (Kutmuda!)
[ORCS CHANTING IN BLACK SPEECH]: Death! (Gurut!)
Death! (Gurut!)
[Lord] of the Earth, of the Earth!
(Dashshu, dashshu!)
[IN QUENYA] Hail Eärendil brightest of the Stars!
(Aiya Eärendil Elenion Ancalima!)
SAURON [IN SINDARIN]: White-glittering slants down...
(Silivren penna míriel...)
SAURON: ...sparkling like jewels!
(...o menel aglar elenath!)
White-glittering slants down...
(Silivren penna míriel...)
SAURON [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  Seven dwarves in stone halls...
(Ombi kuzd gundum-ishi...)
And in darkness bind them.
(Agh burzum-ishi krimpatul.)
[ORCS CHANTING IN BLACK SPEECH]:  One Ring to rule them all!
(Ash nazg durbatulûk!)
One Ring to rule them all!
One Ring...
(Ash nazg...)
THE RING [IN BLACK SPEECH]:  One Ring to-rule-them-all...
(Ash Nazg durbatulûk...)
...One Ring to find them...
(...Ash Nazg gimbatul...)
...in the Darkness bind them...
(...Burzum-ishi krimpatul...)
ARAGORN [IN QUENYA]:  Out of the Great Sea...
(Et Eärello...)
...to Middle-earth I am come.
(...Endorenna utúlien.)
In this place will I abide...
(Sinomë maruvan...)
...and my heirs...
(...ar Hildinyar...)
...unto the ending of the world.
(...tenn' Ambar-metta.)
[IN SINDARIN] Thank you.
(Hannon le.)
[IN SINDARIN] (I Aear cân ven na mar.)