[CHATTERING INDISTINCTLY]
ARAGORN:
You may go no further.
You will not enter Gondor.
[SAILORS LAUGH]
Who are you to deny us passage?
Legolas, fire a warning shot
past the bosun's ear.
Mind your aim.
[YELLS]
Oh!
That's it. Right. We warned you.
Prepare to be boarded.
[SAILORS LAUGH]
CORSAIR BOSUN:
Boarded?
By you and whose army?
This army.
[YELLING]
In there.
What is this place?
[WATER DRIPPING]
Master must go inside the tunnel.
Now that I'm here, I don't think I want to.
It's the only way.
Go in...
...or go back.
I can't go back.
[FRODO GRUNTS]
-What's that smell?
GOLLUM: Orcses' filth.
Orcses come in here sometimes.
Hurry.
This way.
Sméagol?
GOLLUM:
Over here.
Oh!
Aah! Aah!
It's sticky. What is it?
GOLLUM:
You'll see.
Oh, yes.
You will see.
Sméagol?
Sméagol!
Sam.
[GROWLING]
[WHIMPERING]
GALADRIEL:
And you, Frodo Baggins...
...I give you the light of Eärendil,
our most beloved star.
May it be a light for you
in dark places...
...when all other lights go out.
[IN QUENYA] Hail Eärendil brightest of the Stars!
(Aiya Eärendil Elenion Ancalima!)
[SCREECHES]
[HISSING]
GOLLUM [SINGING]:
Naughty little fly
Why does he cry?
Caught in a web
Soon you'll be...
Eaten.
[GRUNTS, YELLS]
Got away, did it, precious?
Not this time.
-Not this time!
-No!
[SCREAMING]
It wasn't us. It wasn't us!
Sméagol wouldn't hurt master.
We promised.
You must believe us.
It was the precious.
The precious made us do it.
[GOLLUM SOBBING]
I have to destroy it, Sméagol.
I have to destroy it for both our sakes.
No!
[SCREAMS]
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
I'm so sorry, Sam.
I'm so sorry.
GALADRIEL:  This task was appointed
to you, Frodo of the Shire.
If you do not find a way...
...no one will.
ÉOMER: The scouts report
Minas Tirith is surrounded.
The lower level's in flames.
Everywhere,
legions of the enemy advance.
Time is against us.
Make ready!
Take heart, Merry.
It will soon be over.
My lady...
...you are fair and brave...
...and have much to live for...
...and many who love you.
I know it is too late to turn aside.
I know there is not much point
now in hoping.
If I were a knight of Rohan,
capable of great deeds...
But I'm not.
I'm a Hobbit.
And I know I can't save Middle-earth.
I just want to help my friends.
Frodo.
Sam.
Pippin.
More than anything,
I wish I could see them again.
ÉOMER:
Prepare to move out!
Make haste.
We ride through the night.
[HORN BLOWING]
To battle.
Back to the gate!
Hurry!
I am steward of the House of Anárion.
Thus have I walked.
And thus now will I sleep.
Gondor is lost.
There is no hope for Men.
Why do the fools fly?
Better to die sooner than late.
For die we must.
No tomb for Denethor
and Faramir.
No long, slow sleep of death embalmed.
We shall burn,
like the heathen kings of old.
Bring wood and oil.
GANDALF:
Steady.
You are soldiers of Gondor.
No matter what comes through that gate,
you will stand your ground.
[ROARING]
SOLDIER:
Run!
Volley!
Fire!
[SHRIEKS]
[ROCKS FALLING]
[GRUNTING]
Let him go, you filth.
[SCREECHES]
Let him go!
You will not touch him again.
Come on and finish it.
[YELLS, GRUNTS]
[SHELOB SQUEALS]
[GRUNTS]
[SHELOB SQUEALING]
Ha! Back!
Mr. Frodo.
Oh, no.
Frodo.
Mr. Frodo.
Wake up.
Don't leave me here alone.
Don't go where I can't follow.
Wake up.
Not asleep.
Dead.
[ORCS GROWLING]
SHAGRAT:
You get back, you scum!
GORBAG:
What's this?
Looks like old Shelob's
been having a bit of fun.
SHAGRAT:
Killed another one, has she?
No.
This fellow ain't dead.
[WHISPERING]
Not dead?
She jabs him with her stinger,
and he goes as limp as a boned fish.
Then she has her way with them.
That's how she likes to feed.
Fresh blood.
Get him to the tower!
Samwise, you fool.
TOWER ORC: This scum will be awake
in a couple of hours.
Then he'll wish he'd never been born.
[WHIMPERS FAINTLY]
[BATTLE SOUNDS IN DISTANCE]
The house of his spirit crumbles.
He is burning.
Already burning.
PIPPIN:
He's not dead.
He's not dead!
No! No!
-Farewell, Peregrin, son of Paladin.
PIPPIN: No! No! No!
I release you from my service.
Go now and die in what way
seems best to you.
Pour oil on the wood!
SOLDIER:
Come on, soldier! Move it!
-Hurry along there! Hurry along!
-Gandalf!
Where is Gandalf?
Gandalf!
GANDALF:
Retreat!
The city is breached!
Fall back to the second level!
Get the women and children out!
Get them out!
Retreat!
SOLDIER:
Come on. Come on.
Move into the city. Kill all in your path.
[ORCS YELLING INDISTINCTLY]
GUARD:
Take them down!
[WOMEN SCREAMING]
GANDALF:
Fight. Fight to the last man!
Fight for your lives!
Gandalf!
Denethor has lost his mind!
He's burning Faramir alive!
Up! Quickly!
[ROARING]
Go back to the abyss.
Fall into the nothingness
that awaits you and your master.
WITCH-KING: Do you not know death
when you see it, old man?
This is my hour.
[WITCH-KING SCREECHING]
Gandalf!
[YELLS]
WITCH-KING:
You have failed.
The world of Men will fall.
[HORN BLOWING]
[ORCS CHANTING]
Courage, Merry.
Courage for our friends.
GOTHMOG:
Form ranks, you maggots. Form ranks!
Pikes in front. Archers behind.
THÉODEN: Éomer, take your éored
down the left flank.
ÉOMER:
Flank ready.
THÉODEN: Gamling, follow the king's
banner down the center.
Grimbold, take your company right
after you pass the wall.
Forth, and fear no darkness!
Arise, arise, Riders of Théoden!
Spears shall be shaken,
shields shall be splintered...
...a sword-day, a red day...
...ere the sun rises!
Whatever happens, stay with me.
I'll look after you.
[CLANGING]
THÉODEN:
Ride now!
Ride! Ride for ruin...
...and the world's ending!
Death!
ALL:
THÉODEN: Death!
ALL: Death!
-Death!
Forth Eorlingas!
[HORNS SOUNDING]
[RIDERS YELLING]
Fire!
Death!
Charge!
Fire at will!
[YELLS]
[BREATHING UNEVENLY]
Set a fire in our flesh.
Stay this madness!
You may triumph in the field of battle
for a day...
...but against the power that has risen
in the east...
...there is no victory.
[YELLS]
No!
You will not take my son from me!
No! No!
Yah!
[YELLS]
Faramir.
[SCREAMING]
So passes Denethor, son of Ecthelion.
Drive them to the river!
Make safe the city!
[OLIPHAUNTS ROARING]
[FOOTSTEPS THUDDING]
[HORN BLOWING]
[HARADRIM CHANTING]
Re-form the line!
Sound the charge! Take them head-on!
Charge!
[YELLS]
MAN 1:
Cut him down!
MAN 2:
Follow me!
Take the reins. Pull him left!
Left!
Aim for their heads!
Bring it down! Bring it down!
Bring it down!
Merry!
[COUGHS]
[GROWLS]
[FELL BEAST ROARS]
[POUNDING]
I didn't think it would end this way.
End?
No, the journey doesn't end here.
Death is just another path...
...one that we all must take.
The grey rain curtain
of this world rolls back...
...and all turns to silver glass.
And then you see it.
What, Gandalf?
See what?
White shores...
...and beyond.
A far green country...
...under a swift sunrise.
Well...
...that isn't so bad.
No.
No, it isn't.
[POUNDING CONTINUES,
TROLL GRUNTS]
Rally to me! To me!
[SCREECHES]
[ROARING]
WITCH-KING:
Feast on his flesh.
I will kill you if you touch him.
WITCH-KING: Do not come between
the Nazgûl and his prey.
[HISSES]
[SCREECHING]
ORC COMMANDER:
Late as usual, pirate scum!
There's knife-work here needs doing.
Come on, you sea rats!
Get off your ships!
There's plenty for the both of us.
May the best Dwarf win.
[YELLS]
WITCH-KING:
You fool.
No man can kill me.
Die now.
[SCREECHES]
[SCREAMS]
I am no man.
[YELLS]
-Fifteen! Sixteen!
GIMLI: Seventeen!
Merry!
[YELLING]
Legolas!
Thirty-three, thirty-four.
[ROARS]
That still only counts as one!
Come on, then. Come on!
THÉODEN:
I know your face...
...Éowyn.
My eyes darken.
No.
I am going to save you.
You already did.
Éowyn...
...my body is broken.
You have to let me go.
[MOUTHING]
I go to my fathers...
...in whose mighty company...
...I shall not now feel ashamed.
Éowyn.
[SOBBING]
Release us.
Bad idea.
Very handy in a tight spot, these lads,
despite the fact they're dead.
You gave us your word.
I hold your oath fulfilled.
Go.
Be at peace.
[SIGHS]
[WIND WHISTLING]
[GRUNTS]
Merry.
No!
PIPPIN:
Merry!
Merry.
Merry, it's me.
It's Pippin.
I knew you'd find me.
PIPPIN:
Yes.
Are you going to leave me?
No, Merry.
I'm going to look after you.
[ORCS GROWLING AND YELLING
IN DISTANCE]
[SNARLS]
Hands off!
That shiny shirt, that's mine.
It's going to the Great Eye,
along with everything else.
SHAGRAT: I don't take orders from
stinking Morgul-rats!
GORBAG: You touch it, and I'll stick
this blade in your gut.
[YELLING]
The scum tried to knife me.
Kill him!
[ROARS]
[FIGHTING IN DISTANCE]
[GRUNTING]
[SNARLS]
That's for Frodo!
And for the Shire!
And that's for my old Gaffer!
[GRUNTING]
Stop your squealing, you dunghill rat.
I'm gonna bleed you like a stuck pig.
[GASPS, DROPS SWORD]
-Not if I stick you first.
-Sam!
[GRUNTS, REMOVES SWORD]
Oh, Sam, I'm so sorry.
Sorry for everything.
SAM: Let's get you out of here.
-It's too late. It's over.
They've taken it. Sam...
...they took the Ring.
Begging your pardon, but they haven't.
I thought I'd lost you.
So I took it.
Only for safekeeping.
Give it to me.
Give me the Ring, Sam.
[VOICE OF THE RING WHISPERING]
[VOICE ECHOING]
Sam.
Give me the Ring.
[WHISPERING STOPS]
[IN NORMAL VOICE]
You must understand.
The Ring is my burden.
It will destroy you, Sam.
[BREATHING WITH DIFFICULTY]
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
We best find you some clothes.
You can't go walking through Mordor
in naught but your skin.
SAM:
We did it, Mr. Frodo.
We made it to Mordor.
FRODO:
There are so many of them.
We'll never get through unseen.
It's him, the Eye.
We have to go in there, Mr. Frodo.
There's nothing for it.
Come on. Let's just make it
down the hill for starters.
Frodo has passed beyond my sight.
The darkness is deepening.
If Sauron had the Ring,
we would know it.
It's only a matter of time.
He has suffered a defeat, yes...
...but behind the walls of Mordor,
our enemy is regrouping.
Let him stay there.
Let him rot! Why should we care?
Because 10,000 Orcs now stand
between Frodo and Mount Doom.
I've sent him to his death.
No.
There is still hope for Frodo.
He needs time and safe passage
across the plains of Gorgoroth.
-We can give him that.
-How?
Draw out Sauron's armies.
Empty his lands.
Then we gather our full strength
and march on the Black Gate.
[COUGHS]
We cannot achieve victory
through strength of arms.
ARAGORN:
Not for ourselves.
But we can give Frodo his chance
if we keep Sauron's Eye fixed upon us.
Keep him blind to all else that moves.
A diversion.
Certainty of death...
...small chance of success...
...what are we waiting for?
Sauron will suspect a trap.
He will not take the bait.
Oh, I think he will.
[CRACKLING]
SAURON [IN SINDARIN]: White-glittering slants down...
(Silivren penna míriel...)
SAURON: ...sparkling like... (...o menel aglar...)
Long have you hunted me.
SAURON: ...jewels!
(...elenath!)
Long have I eluded you.
No more.
Behold the Sword of Elendil.
White-glittering slants down...
(Silivren penna míriel...)
SAURON [IN BLACK SPEECH]:
(Ombi kur gundum-ishi...)
And in darkness bind them.
(Agh burzum-ishi krimpatul.)
ÉOWYN:
The city has fallen silent.
There is no warmth left in the sun.
It grows so cold.
It's just the damp
of the first spring rain.
I do not believe this darkness
will endure.
[HORN BLOWING]
SAM:
Look, the Orcs...
...they're moving off.
You see, Mr. Frodo...
...some luck at last.
ORC SERGEANT:
Move it, you slugs!
Come on! Faster!
Come along, you scum...
I'll whip you down to the bone, you...
Come on!
What have I told you?!
[ORC SERGEANT YELLING
INDISTINCTLY]
Get up!
Come on, you slugs!
You two are going straight
to the front line!
Now, move it! Go on!
Fall in! Move it!
To the Gate, you slugs!
Now, move it!
Don't you know we're at war?
[ORCS GROWLING AND GRUNTING]
ORC SERGEANT:
Company, halt!
[HORN BLOWING]
Inspection!
FRODO:
Sam, help me.
SAM:
Mr. Frodo!
Stand up, Mr. Frodo.
Stand up!
FRODO:
It's so heavy.
[GROWLS AND SNORTS]
SAM:
Oh, no.
[ROARS]
What do I do?
What do we do?
FRODO: Hit me.
SAM: What?
FRODO:
Hit me, Sam. Start fighting.
SAM:
Get off of me!
Nobody pushes me, you filthy maggot.
Break it up! Break it up!
Oi! I'll have your guts if you don't
shut this rabble down!
FRODO:
Go, Sam. Now!
Move along, scum!
Back in the line!
You maggots!
Get back into the line,
you slugs!
Dig it, you slugs. Move it.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
Move it!
[GRUNTS]
[PANTING]
I can't...
I can't manage the Ring, Sam.
It's... It's...
It's such a weight to carry.
It...
Such a weight.
We're going that way.
Straight as we can.
There's no point carrying anything
we're not sure to need.
[CLANGING]
Mr. Frodo.
Look.
There is light...
...and beauty up there...
...that no shadow can touch.
[WHEEZING]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
Take mine.
There's a few drops left.
There will be none left
for the return journey.
I don't think there will be
a return journey, Mr. Frodo.
[VOICE OF THE RING WHISPERING]
Frodo, get down!
Hide!
[GRUNTS]
Frodo!
Where are they?
Let the Lord of the Black Land come forth!
Let justice be done upon him!
[GATE CREAKING]
My master, Sauron the Great,
bids thee welcome.
Is there any in this rout
with authority to treat with me?
We do not come to treat with Sauron...
...faithless and accursed.
Tell your master this:
The armies of Mordor must disband.
He is to depart these lands,
never to return.
Aha. Old Greybeard.
I have a token I was bidden
to show thee.
Frodo.
-Silence.
-No!
Silence!
The Halfling was dear to thee, I see.
Know that he suffered greatly
at the hands of his host.
[GROWLS]
Who would've thought one so small
could endure so much pain?
And he did, Gandalf.
He did.
[LAUGHS]
And who is this?
Isildur's heir?
It takes more to make a king
than a broken Elvish blade.
[YELLS]
I guess that concludes negotiations.
I do not believe it.
I will not.
[GROWLING]
Pull back.
Pull back!
[ORCS CHANTING]
SAM:
It's gone, Mr. Frodo.
The light's passed on,
away towards the north.
Something's drawn its gaze.
Hold your ground! Hold your ground.
Sons of Gondor, of Rohan, my brothers!
I see in your eyes...
...the same fear that would take
the heart of me.
A day may come
when the courage of Men fails...
...when we forsake our friends
and break all bonds of fellowship.
But it is not this day.
An hour of wolves
and shattered shields...
...when the age of Men
comes crashing down.
But it is not this day.
This day we fight!
By all that you hold dear
on this good earth...
...I bid you stand, Men of the West!
[STEAM HISSING]
[GRUNTS]
Never thought I'd die fighting
side by side with an Elf.
What about side by side with a friend?
Aye.
I could do that.
Do you remember the Shire,
Mr. Frodo?
It'll be spring soon.
And the orchards will be in blossom.
And the birds will be nesting
in the hazel thicket.
And they'll be sowing
the summer barley in the lower fields...
...and eating the first
of the strawberries with cream.
Do you remember
the taste of strawberries?
[HOARSELY]
No, Sam.
I can't recall the taste of food...
...nor the sound of water...
...nor the touch of grass.
I'm...
...naked in the dark.
There's-- There's nothing.
No veil between me
and the wheel of fire.
I can see him...
...with my waking eyes.
Then let us be rid of it...
...once and for all.
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
I can't carry it for you...
...but I can carry you.
Come on!
[SAURON GROWLING]
SAURON:
Aragorn.
[SAURON WHISPERING
INDISTINCTLY]
Elessar.
For Frodo.
[YELLING]
Look, Mr. Frodo.
A doorway.
We're almost there.
Clever Hobbits to climb so high!
[SCREAMS, GRUNTS]
Mustn't go that way.
Mustn't hurt the precious.
You swore!
You swore on the precious!
Sméagol promised!
Sméagol lied.
[YELLS]
[COUGHS]
[FELL BEASTS ROARING]
[RINGWRAITHS SCREECHING]
[SCREAMS]
Frodo!
[RINGWRAITH SCREECHING]
Eagles.
The eagles are coming!
Frodo!
I'm here, Sam.
Destroy it!
Go on! Now!
Throw it in the fire!
[PANTING]
What are you waiting for?
Just let it go!
[VOICE OF THE RING WHISPERING]
The Ring is mine.
No.
No!
[RINGWRAITHS SCREECHING]
[FRODO YELLING]
[ROARING]
[FRODO AND GOLLUM GRUNTING]
[AGONIZED SCREAM]
[GROANING]
[VOICE MUTED]
[GOLLUM CACKLING]
GOLLUM:
Yes!
Precious! Precious!
[LAUGHING]
[ROARS]
Give me your hand!
Take my hand!
No!
Don't you let go.
Don't let go.
Reach!
[SCREECHING]
[SCREECHING,
DEEP RUMBLING]
[CRACKING]
Frodo!
[VOICE MUTED]
[EXHALES SOFTLY]
It's gone.
It's done.
SAM:
Yes, Mr. Frodo.
It's over now.
[EXPLOSION]
[PANTING SOFTLY]
I can see the Shire.
The Brandywine River.
Bag End.
Gandalf's fireworks.
The lights in the Party Tree.
Rosie Cotton dancing.
She had ribbons in her hair.
If ever I was to marry someone...
...it would've been her.
It would've been her.
[SAM SOBBING]
I'm glad to be with you,
Samwise Gamgee...
...here at the end of all things.
[EAGLES SCREECHING]
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
Gandalf?
[LAUGHING]
Frodo!
Gimli!
[VOICE MUTED]
Now come the days of the king.
May they be blessed.
[SIGHS]
[CHEERING]
This day does not belong to one man...
...but to all.
Let us together rebuild this world...
...that we may share
in the days of peace.
ARAGORN [IN QUENYA]:  Out of the Great Sea...
(Et Eärello...)
...to Middle-earth I am come.
(...Endorenna utúlien.)
In this place will I abide...
(Sinomë maruvan...)
...and my heirs...
(...ar Hildinyar...)
...unto the ending of the world.
(...tenn' Ambar-metta.)
[IN SINDARIN] Thank you.
(Hannon le.)
[CROWD APPLAUDS]
[LAUGHS]
[IN ENGLISH]
My friends...
...you bow to no one.
FRODO:
And thus it was.
A Fourth Age of Middle-earth began.
And the Fellowship of the Ring...
...though eternally bound
by friendship and love...
...was ended.
Thirteen months to the day since Gandalf
sent us on our long journey...
...we found ourselves
looking upon a familiar sight.
We were home.
Hi.
[HOBBITS CHATTERING
AND LAUGHING]
Hey, watch the pumpkin.
Hey!
MALE PATRON:
More of the same, Rosie.
Good night, lads.
[EXHALES]
[LAUGHING]
[GUESTS APPLAUDING
AND CHEERING]
PIPPIN:
Hm?
FRODO:  How do you pick up the threads
of an old life?
How do you go on...
...when in your heart
you begin to understand...
...there is no going back?
There are some things
that time cannot mend...
...some hurts that go too deep...
...that have taken hold.
[DOOR OPENS]
SAM:
Mr. Frodo?
What is it?
It's been four years to the day
since Weathertop, Sam.
It's never really healed.
"There and Back Again: A Hobbit's Tale
by Bilbo Baggins.
And The Lord of the Rings
by Frodo Baggins."
You finished it.
FRODO:
Not quite.
There's room for a little more.
FRODO:  Bilbo once told me his part
in this tale would end...
...that each of us must come and go
in the telling.
Bilbo's story was now over.
There would be no more journeys
for him...
...save one.
BILBO [WEAKLY]:
Tell me again, lad, where are we going?
FRODO:
To the harbor, Bilbo.
The Elves have accorded you
a special honor...
...a place on the last ship
to leave Middle-earth.
Frodo...
...any chance of seeing
that old Ring of mine again?
The one I gave you.
I'm sorry, Uncle.
I'm afraid I lost it.
Oh.
Pity.
I should like to have held it
one last time.
[SEAGULLS CAWING]
Oh!
Well, here's a sight
I have never seen before.
The power of the Three Rings is ended.
The time has come...
...for the dominion of Men.
[IN SINDARIN] (I Aear cân ven na mar.)
I think I'm...
...quite ready
for another adventure.
Farewell...
...my brave Hobbits.
My work is now finished.
Here at last,
on the shores of the sea...
...comes the end of our Fellowship.
I will not say, "Do not weep"...
...for not all tears are an evil.
It is time, Frodo.
SAM:
What does he mean?
We set out to save the Shire, Sam.
And it has been saved.
But not for me.
You don't mean that.
You can't leave.
The last pages are for you, Sam.
FRODO:
My dear Sam:
You cannot always be torn in two.
You will have to be one and whole
for many years.
You have so much to enjoy
and to be and to do.
Your part in the story will go on.
Well...
...I'm back.
[CHUCKLES]
[ANNIE LENNOX SINGING
"INTO THE WEST"]
Lay down
Your sweet and weary head
Night is falling
You have come
To journey's end
Sleep now
And dream
Of the ones who came before
They are calling
From across
The distant shore
Why do you weep?
What are these tears
Upon your face?
Soon you will see
All of your fears
Will pass away
Safe in my arms
You're only sleeping
What can you see
On the horizon?
Why do the white gulls
Call?
Across the sea
A pale moon rises
The ships have come
To carry you home
And all will turn
To silver glass
A light on the water
All souls pass
Hope fades
Into the world of night
Through shadows falling
Out of memory and time
Don't say
We have come now to the end
White shores are calling
You and I will meet again
And you'll be here
In my arms
Just sleeping
What can you see
On the horizon?
Why do the white gulls
Call?
Across the sea
A pale moon rises
The ships have come
To carry you home
And all will turn
To silver glass
A light on the water
Grey ships pass
Into the West
[English & Sindarin & Quenya & Rohirric - US - SDH - v1.0]